<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-04T04:49:51-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">nyayava’s blog</title><subtitle>language, art, life, random thoughts
</subtitle><author><name>nyayava</name></author><entry><title type="html">OECD and illicit trade detection</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/10/04/illicit-trade.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OECD and illicit trade detection" /><published>2025-10-04T04:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-04T04:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/10/04/illicit-trade</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/10/04/illicit-trade.html"><![CDATA[<p>A <a href="https://www.oecd.org/en/publications/global-trade-in-fakes_74c81154-en.html">study</a> based on 2021 global customs seizure data studied key characteristics of trade in counterfeit goods and estimated its scale, impact, and effects on the EU.</p>

<p>The findings indicate that counterfeit and pirated goods accounted for <strong>2.3%</strong> of global trade (equivalent to USD 467 billion or 約69兆円). Within the EU, fake goods made up 4.7% of total imports. In terms of product categories, 50 out of 96 categories are affected. High-value goods such as clothing, footwear, leather products, and electronics are the top targets. The data also highlights the presence of dangerous counterfeit items, including automotive parts and pharmaceuticals. Trade routes are continuously evolving, as counterfeiters increasingly exploit international shipping channels and adopt localization strategies to produce fake goods closer to end markets. The General Trade-Related Index of Counterfeiting (GTRIC) estimates the likelihood of specific countries being major sources of counterfeit exports, with China, Bangladesh, Lebanon, the Syrian Arab Republic, and Turkey ranking high.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="how-are-illicit-trades-detected">How are illicit trades detected?</h4>
<p>Ideally, if the goal is to prevent illicit trade, all packages would be inspected, but this isn’t possible due to the sheer volume of global trade. Instead, only a small share of shipments are inspected based on risk targeting by customs officers who flag items as suspicious through documentation, profiling, or physical inspection. The study mentions some characteristics that signal suspicious shipment:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Small parcels</strong>: 79% of seizures in 2020-2021  involved parcels with fewer than 10 items. This is extremely hard to detect because invoices are vague (e.g. “stuff” or “daily necessities”) and air cargo hubs are not equipped to screen them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Localisation tactics</strong>: Counterfeiters often ship packaging and component parts separately, or they assemble goods inside FTZs or near the destination. This strategy reduces the chance of detection and avoids scrutiny. 
There may be other signals, such as suspicious route that detours through FTZs, unusually low declared value, mismatch between reported product and image scanned product, history of sender, and so on.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>As for <strong>risk indices</strong> to target inspection, the GTRIC-e and GTRIC-p indices are used. GTRIC-e (economies) measures a country’s (economy’s) propensity to be a source of counterfeit exports. GTRIC-p (products) measures a product category’s propensity to be prone to counterfeiting.</p>

<p>From what I understand, these indices are not estimated based on statistical models, but are estimated based on summary statistics of observed data. For example, for GTRIC-p, the counterfeiting factor index is calculated based on data as the proportion of seizures of a particular product relative to the total trade volume of that product across countries. This is calculated for all product categories, so we get a sampling distribution of proportions across categories. The distribution is highly right-skewed to the right, with most products having a small index, so a log transformation is applied. A left-truncated normal distribution is then assumed to estimate the probabilities of counterfeiting a given product.</p>

<p>The study use two datasets: trade data and seizure data.</p>
<ul>
  <li>In the trade data, each observation is defined by a product category, country pair, and year. Variables include the product code, origin and destination countries, and the value of imports.</li>
  <li>The seizure data includes around 297,000 records from 2020–2021. Variables cover product category, country of origin, transport mode, value of goods, and quantity. However, there are coverage gaps, as not all customs authorities share data, and enforcement levels vary across regions.</li>
</ul>

<p>The report calls for improved risk profiling through the use of AI, enhanced data sharing, and closer collaboration with industries and rights holders who have expertise in identifying counterfeit goods.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="improving-detection-accuracy">Improving detection accuracy</h4>
<p>It seems there are opportunities to improve detection accuracy from a data collection and modeling perspective.</p>

<p>What kinds of data would be most useful to collect? Currently, they have access to basic variables like origin, destination, product type, declared value, quantity, and transport mode. Perhaps adding more granular socioeconomic indicators of the source region, beyond just the country level, could help?</p>

<p>As for modeling, using statistical models to estimate the probability of a shipment being illicit based on combinations of these variables might improve accuracy. However, this is a probably very hard detection problem, regardless of additional variables we collect and refinement of modeling. Given the occurrence rate of about 2%, within the context of massive trade volumes, this is a rare event modeling. The prediction accuracy is only going to be so high. On top of that, customs officials are already stretched thin, inspecting drugs, weapons, terrorism, and other risks.</p>

<h4 id="holding-counterfeiter-accountable">Holding counterfeiter accountable</h4>
<p>Instead of treating this solely as a prediction or detection problem, could we also approach it from the perspective of accountability? For example, even if a small number of counterfeiters are identified, making sure that they face real consequences, such as fines, penalties, or bans from trading, could act as a deterrent and also partially address the revenue losses caused by illicit trade. We can measure the effect of such implementation.</p>

<h4 id="incentives-for-supply-and-demand-of-counterfeit-goods">Incentives for supply and demand of counterfeit goods</h4>
<p>Another perspective is the incentives structure that drive counterfeiters to engage in illicit trade, as well as the demand for counterfeit goods—both intentional and unintentional. The <a href="https://www.oecd.org/en/publications/why-do-countries-import-fakes_8a4a4508-en.html">report</a> examines the demand side, distinguishing between two types of consumers. Unintentional demand comes from consumers who are deceived; this group accounts for 46% of counterfeit and pirated imports. Intentional demand involves consumers who knowingly purchase counterfeits, often due to price or accessibility; this accounts for approximately 54% of counterfeit and pirated imports between 2017 and 2019. The report also identifies several factors correlated with the value of counterfeit imports. Countries with higher GDP per capita tend to import fewer fakes, while countries with better trade and transport infrastructure, and greater internet use, tertiary education, are positively correlated with higher volumes of counterfeit imports (possibly by the ability to search for good bargains online).</p>

<h4 id="fake-goods-and-fake-information">Fake goods and fake information</h4>
<p>There appears to be a connection between the challenge of detecting fake products and the broader issue of fake information on digital platforms. This raises more philosophical questions: What does it mean for something to be fake, and why do fakes emerge in the first place? How are fakes detected and confirmed in each case? What is the required cost for detecting and proving something as fake? How are those responsible held accountable? And why do people buy, see value, or even spread fake goods or information—whether knowingly or not?</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A study based on 2021 global customs seizure data studied key characteristics of trade in counterfeit goods and estimated its scale, impact, and effects on the EU.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">OECD and illicit trade prevention</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/10/03/illicit-trade.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OECD and illicit trade prevention" /><published>2025-10-03T11:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-03T11:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/10/03/illicit-trade</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/10/03/illicit-trade.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a summary and reflection on OECD’s efforts to prevent illicit trade.</p>

<p><strong>Illicit trade</strong> refers to the illegal production, movement, and sale of goods and services—including counterfeit (fake) products, pirated products (e.g. unauthorized copies), fake medicines, cultural artefacts, smuggled goods, wildlife trafficking, and illegal logging. (Human trafficking is in a separate domain in the OECD.) Often operated by criminal networks, illicit trade threatens public health, safety and undermines legal markets.</p>

<p>Addressing it requires cross-border and cross-sector cooperation. The OECD works with governments, international organizations, and private sector partners to identify and map illicit trade risks.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="vulnerabilities-of-free-trade-zones-to-illicit-trade">Vulnerabilities of free trade zones to illicit trade</h4>
<p>OECD Working Party on Countering Illicit Trade (<a href="https://one.oecd.org/document/C/MIN%282025%2911/en/pdf">WP-CIT)</a> was restructured in 2025 as a platform for member countries to exchange information, including evidence on the scale, scope, and trends of the problem, as well as best practices for preventing illicit trade.</p>

<p>Another issue the WP-CIT deals with is the recent abuse of Free Trade Zones (<a href="https://www.oecd.org/en/topics/sub-issues/free-trade-zones.html">FTZs</a>). FTZs are geographic areas where goods entering the zone are either exempt from or subject to relaxed import and export duties. The idea dates back to 1937 in Ireland, and gained global momentum after World War II and, as of 2025, there are approximately 5,400 FTZs operating across 135 countries. The purpose is to make trading cheaper and faster by simplifying procedures, encouraging investment by attracting companies looking to reduce transportation and logistics costs, and bringing economic benefits to both host countries and businesses located within the zones. However, FTZs also are major transit points for illicit goods, as criminals exploit supervisory gaps to smuggle or divert illicit products through these zones.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="code-for-countering-illicit-trade">Code for countering illicit trade</h4>
<p>To counter illicit trade, the OECD issued a <strong><a href="https://legalinstruments.oecd.org/en/instruments/OECD-LEGAL-0454">Recommendation in 2019</a></strong> aimed at improving transparency and oversight in FTZs. It includes a Code of Conduct that encourages tracking data, sharing it with authorities when needed, and identifying compliant vs. non-compliant zones.</p>

<p>The Code outlines five key areas:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Legal Framework – Authorities (such as the police, customs) must have the power to inspect, monitor, and enforce rules within FTZs.</li>
  <li>Transparency and Risk Assessment – FTZ operators must disclose client identities, maintain records, and share data. Zones are also expected to publish annual risk indicators.</li>
  <li>International Cooperation – Authorities should share information across borders to tackle cross-border illicit trade.</li>
  <li>Domestic Cooperation – Government agencies should exchange information and raise awareness among private actors like shippers and logistics firms.</li>
  <li>Promoting Clean FTZs – Governments should incentivize compliance, for example by applying stricter checks on goods from non-compliant zones.</li>
</ol>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="evaluation-of-the-code">Evaluation of the Code</h4>
<p>A survey was conducted between November 2024 and March 2025 among all adherents to the OECD Recommendation on Countering Illicit Trade, which includes the 38 OECD member countries and the European Union. In total, 20 countries responded to the survey. Of these, 12 have Free Trade Zones (FTZs) in place: Canada, Colombia, Costa Rica, Czechia, France, Italy, Israel, Korea, Lithuania, Slovak Republic, Turkey, UK, US, EU. Te remaining 8, including countries like Australia and Japan, do not have FTZs in their territories. This suggests that 19 adherent countries did not respond to the survey. It’s worth noting that many countries outside the OECD also operate FTZs, including the UAE, China, and Morocco. However, the OECD can only formally monitor its member countries and official adherents to the Recommendation, so we lack the complete picture of the management of FTZs worldwide. The survey consisted of 24 questions, mostly in yes/no or multiple-choice format, with optional free-text responses for providing examples or elaboration.</p>

<p>Key Findings from the 12 OECD countries with FTZs:</p>
<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Legal Frameworks: Almost all respondents with FTZs have laws empowering authorities to inspect, monitor, and enforce rules within the zones. However, only 6 have a legal framework that prohibits individuals convicted of illicit trade from operating in FTZs. This sounds surprising to me, but FTZs often operate under special regimes (e.g., customs exemptions, reduced oversight), and laws don’t always explicitly extend general criminal restrictions to activities within FTZs.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Transparency and Risk Assessment: About half require FTZ operators to disclose client identities. Many countries report monitoring activities and publishing risk indicators, but implementation is inconsistent.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>International Cooperation: 8 have designated authorities for cross-border information sharing.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Domestic Cooperation: 10 report active inter-agency coordination, including information sharing and reporting suspicious activities.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Encouraging Clean FTZs (Code of Conduct) :Only 6 have formally implemented the OECD Code of Conduct. Some countries rely instead on domestic regulatory frameworks rather than adopting the OECD’s approach directly.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="limitations-and-extensions">Limitations and extensions</h4>
<p>There are approximately 5,400 FTZs worldwide, while only about 350 are located within OECD countries, based on 2018 data, meaning OECD FTZs make up just around <strong>6% of the global total</strong>. The survey response rate for the OECD Recommendation was relatively low: 19 out of 39 adherents did not respond. The results are therefore based primarily on the 12 that responded with FTZs. This means the majority of FTZs under OECD jurisdiction remain unaccounted for in the survey. As a result, the findings are not representative of the broader picture. In fact, they could reflect a more positive view of code compliance, as countries with stronger systems may be more likely to respond. Additionally, the OECD Code of Conduct is voluntary, which limits enforcement. The small number of FTZs the OECD can monitor, combined with the optional nature of the code, means this is just a starting point for understanding the overall health of the international trading system, especially in identifying weak points where illicit trade can occur.</p>

<p>Even among the 12 countries with FTZs that responded, only 6 have adopted the Code of Conduct. The OECD report emphasizes the importance of <strong>promoting awareness</strong> of the Recommendation and the Code through presentations at international events, training sessions, and pilot certifications for ‘clean FTZs.’</p>

<p>While encouraging adoption of the Code of Conduct is likely important, it is still unclear <strong>how effective the Code actually is in preventing, detecting, and holding illicit traders accountable?</strong></p>

<p>To understand this issue better, another question is: <strong>How is illicit trade actually identified</strong> in the first place? And <strong>what kind of data is recorded</strong> at key transit points, in FTZs within and outside the OECD’s oversight?</p>

<p>If the goal is to improve public health and protect legal markets, then it’s not enough to just enforce rules and we also need the right <strong>metrics to measure their impacts on the ground</strong>. For example, even if the OECD Code of Conduct is adopted, it could unintentionally shift illicit trade to other pathways or create loopholes. Possible metrics that may be of importance are: the volume and value of goods moving through FTZs, the types of goods most frequently involved in seizures (e.g. tobacco, pharmaceuticals), origin and destination countries linked to high-risk shipments, number of inspections, violations, or prosecutions within FTZs, health or safety incidents tied to counterfeit or illicit goods. These indicators could help authorities assess not only whether FTZs are secure, but also whether interventions are truly supporting broader goals like public health and market integrity.</p>

<p>Also, Even if all OECD countries with FTZs adopt the Code of Conduct, <strong>how do non-OECD FTZs affect them?</strong> After all, trade doesn’t happen only within OECD borders; goods frequently pass through or originate from countries like China and others that either don’t follow the Code or where compliance is unknown.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a summary and reflection on OECD’s efforts to prevent illicit trade.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">OECD trade policy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/10/03/oecd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OECD trade policy" /><published>2025-10-03T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-03T10:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/10/03/oecd</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/10/03/oecd.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a summary and reflection on trade policies, as well as OECD’s efforts to prevent illicit trade.</p>

<h4 id="trade-policy-methods-and-impacts">Trade policy: methods and impacts</h4>
<p>Trade policy refers to the rules and regulations a country uses to manage its imports, exports, and international economic relationships. These regulations directly affect how much countries export and import, which in turn impacts GDP, food prices (both domestically and internationally), producer income, food security, and even environmental outcomes, depending on the types of production practices the regulations encourage or discourage.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>One core element of trade policy is <strong>tariffs</strong>, or import duties – taxes placed on goods entering the country. The mechanism is: the U.S. importer pays the tariff to the government, then raises the price charged to U.S. customers to cover that cost, U.S. consumers pay more. Because imported goods become more expensive, the volume of foreign products entering the market typically decreases.</p>

    <p>Potential pros of tariffs include generating government revenue through the collection of import taxes. Tariffs also encourage consumers to purchase domestically produced goods, which can boost domestic industries and create more domestic jobs. This can strengthen economic security by reducing reliance on foreign suppliers, especially for critical or strategic goods.</p>

    <p>Potential cons of tariffs include placing a financial burden on consumers, who end up paying higher prices for imported goods. If domestic producers cannot scale up production quickly, this could lead to shortages of products. Tariffs can also trigger retaliation from other countries, which may impose their own tariffs in response, possibly hurting exporters by reducing the amount of goods they’re able to sell abroad. Also, with reduced competition from foreign producers, domestic industries may become less efficient, which can harm the domestic economy over time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>While tariffs on imports limit goods coming into a country, <strong>taxes on exports</strong> restrict goods leaving.</p>

    <p>Like import tariffs, export taxes generate government revenue, as exporters must pay a tax to sell abroad. Because it becomes more expensive to export, producers may be incentivized to sell domestically, which can help stabilize local prices.</p>

    <p>However, to stay competitive in foreign markets, exporters often lower their prices, reducing their net revenue. Over time, this can hurt producers’ income. Smaller export volumes can also lead to loss of international buyers, who may switch to more stable and reliable suppliers elsewhere.</p>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a summary and reflection on trade policies, as well as OECD’s efforts to prevent illicit trade.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On communicating the option</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/communicate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On communicating the option" /><published>2025-09-30T09:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-30T09:10:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/communicate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/communicate.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on communicating your policy option to your client.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>Now is the time to communicate your policy option to your audience, which could be your client. The purpose is to explain your analysis of the policy (by analysis, we mean the cost-benefit and trade-off analysis, not the outcomes after implementation) and to convince them that this is the best option. This stage involves dialogue, and I think it’s possible your client may not be fully convinced or may raise new issues that need to be addressed. You may need to revisit previous steps to address their concerns and complete the story.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on communicating your policy option to your client.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On deciding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/decide.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On deciding" /><published>2025-09-30T09:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-30T09:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/decide</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/decide.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on deciding on one policy among the narrowed list constructed in the previous step.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>This step is about making a final call on the “best” policy, acting as if you are the decision maker. Compare the outcomes of the narrowed options, weighing costs, benefits, and risks. If the choice is unclear, it may signal unresolved trade-offs or uncertainties that need refining, which in that case revisit the previous step. Also, apply the “twenty-dollar-bill” test: if the policy seems so good, why hasn’t it already been adopted? This can help uncover hidden barriers or resistance.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on deciding on one policy among the narrowed list constructed in the previous step.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On confronting the trade-offs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/tradeoff.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On confronting the trade-offs" /><published>2025-09-30T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-30T08:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/tradeoff</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/tradeoff.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on projecting (or predicting) the outcome of each policy options.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>If there is a single option that is better in all aspects considered, then there is no <strong>trade-off among the outcomes of different options</strong>. Some policy options are better in certain aspects, while others perform better in different areas in terms of the outcome (again, not to be confused with trade-offs among the options themselves). For example, instead of simply comparing “more police patrols” versus “new police vehicles,” compare the actual crime reduction each option might achieve and the cost savings they offer.</p>

<p>Trade-offs often involve <strong>balancing costs and benefits</strong>, so it helps to <strong>standardize metrics</strong> in monetary terms to allow for direct comparison. However, some things, like the value of life, are difficult to quantify in dollars, so break-even threshold analysis can be used to determine the minimum benefits needed to justify the costs.</p>

<p>Another helpful concept is the <strong>margin</strong>; the smallest incremental change in cost, and comparing the corresponding change in outcome. For example, what cost is required to achieve an additional X units of outcome? Then, compare this cost-effectiveness across different options.</p>

<p>Then comes the step to <strong>narrow the list</strong> to the most promising options using a base scenario as a reference point. The base scenario doesn’t have to be business as usual; it can reflect the outcome of a policy that has already been implemented. The final, narrowed list (which can contain multiple options) should be both relatively effective and feasible to implement.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on projecting (or predicting) the outcome of each policy options.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On projecting the outcome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On projecting the outcome" /><published>2025-09-30T07:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-30T07:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/project</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/project.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on projecting (or predicting) the outcome of each policy options.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>Projecting outcomes means making a <strong>reasonable prediction about the results</strong> of implementing a policy using sound methods. This can include building statistical models to estimate outcomes, applying common sense to suggest feasible ranges, or using qualitative reasoning such as case studies. The projection should include both the magnitude of the expected outcome and the uncertainty around it, often expressed as a range rather than a single point estimate.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>One useful approach is <strong>break-even (threshold) analysis</strong>, which <strong>sets a minimum bar for success</strong> by answering the question: “What is the least the policy must achieve to justify its cost? For example, if you have $1 million to reduce juvenile crime, you might ask whether a 1%, 5%, 10%, or 15% reduction would be enough to justify that investment. Then, you assess whether the policy can realistically achieve this minimum threshold, evaluate its plausibility, estimate the probability of failure, and consider the costs of accepting that failure.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Sensitivity analysis</strong> tests how outcomes change when input assumptions or variable values vary. It helps determine how much an assumption can change before the policy result falls outside the desired range.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When exact predictions aren’t feasible, <strong>scenario-based robust policy analysis</strong> can be used. This method compares a policy’s performance, without requiring precise predictions, across multiple future scenarios to identify options that perform reasonably well under a wide range of possible futures. This approach can be used for climate policy problems, where long-term analysis is required but the probability distribution of future climate outcomes is highly uncertain.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When projecting outcomes, beware of <strong>optimism bias</strong>; it’s the tendency to overlook risks and failures. Be realistic about potential future problems like budget cuts or unintended side effects.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I think there is also a phenomenon where implementing a policy can change people’s behavior that then affects the policy outcome.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’m interested in learning about qualitative methods for predicting outcomes, and in comparing them with quantitative approaches to understand when each is most useful.</p>

<p>There are a few more topics in this chapter, but I’ll leave it here for now.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on projecting (or predicting) the outcome of each policy options.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On selecting the criteria</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/criteria.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On selecting the criteria" /><published>2025-09-30T05:40:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-30T05:40:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/criteria</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/criteria.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on selecting the criteria for evaluating the outcome and assessing the practicality of policy implementation.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="criteria-for-evaluating-the-outcome">Criteria for evaluating the outcome</h4>
<p>This is the evaluative plotline, where you decide the criteria to assess the outcomes of a policy (not to be confused with criteria used to directly compare policy options, but rather to evaluate their projected outcomes first, which you then may compare).</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>A common criterion is <strong>efficiency</strong>, which in this case roughly translates to <strong>maximizing public interest</strong> (note that this differs from corporate efficiency which focuses on profit on one side).</p>

    <p>One way to measure efficiency is <strong>cost-effectiveness analysis (CE)</strong>, which assesses how well a policy achieves the desired quantity or nature of an output without assigning a monetary value to the outcome. My understanding is that CE analysis focuses on achieving a specific <strong>fixed outcome</strong> using the least resources or cost, or alternatively, uses <strong>fixed resources</strong> to compare different possible outputs. For example, in an earthquake-prone city upgrading building safety—a fixed desired outcome—the costs include disruption to residents. CE framework may propose to minimize these costs, like scheduling construction in one season rather than another, organizing so that not all stores are closed all at once, etc.</p>

    <p><strong>Cost-benefit analysis (CBA)</strong> evaluates the actual <em>value</em> of a policy’s outcomes in monetary terms. CBA calculates the net benefit by subtracting all costs from the total projected benefits, sometimes expressing this as a ratio. Because assigning monetary values to outcomes can be challenging, CEA is more commonly used.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Another evaluative criterion is <strong>equality, equity, fairness, or justice</strong>. These concepts aren’t defined in the book, but one example is affirmative action in university admissions. Some see it as promoting diverse learning environments or encouraging access to higher education for underrepresented groups. Others see it as unfair, especially if admission rates don’t reflect the proportion of applicants, disadvantaging larger groups with similar qualifications.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Other possible evaluative criteria include <strong>freedom</strong> (e.g., freedom from government interference, free markets, or capitalism).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Process values</strong> also matter, such as <strong>public participation, openness, transparency, and procedural fairness</strong>. However, note that greater participation doesn’t always mean more democracy, since those with more time and resources may disproportionately shape outcomes.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="prioritizing-evaluative-criteria">Prioritizing evaluative criteria</h4>
<p>There are three general approaches to weighting different evaluative criteria.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>One is to <strong>let existing government and officials decide</strong>, assuming they represent the interests of the public.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Another is for <strong>analysts to impose weights</strong> themselves, for example, to give more consideration to groups or values that may be underrepresented.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The third approach is to prioritize criteria based on <strong>rights</strong>, such as the right to privacy; however, which rights are valued can change over time and differ across societies.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="criteria-for-assessing-practicality">Criteria for assessing practicality</h4>
<p>While we’ve discussed criteria for assessing the outcomes of policy options, another type of criteria to consider is for assessing the practicality of implementing those options. The main ones are legality, political acceptability, administrative robustness, improvability, and policy sustainability.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Legality</strong> - policy must not violate constitutional or common law rights. This sounds obvious, but even this is violated these days under the current administration.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Political acceptability</strong> - in thinking about this, distinguish whether low acceptability comes from too much opposition or simply too little support; the latter could happen because of disinterest or lack of awareness, not necessarily opposition.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Robustness</strong> - whether the policy can still produce acceptable outcomes even with poor implementation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Improvability</strong> is about whether the policy leaves room to be improved over time, especially by those involved in implementation. This component makes policy analysis iterative rather than one-time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Policy sustainability</strong> seems related to robustness, but over time and across changing political leadership or environments.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>For all these criteria, it’s helpful to characterize them both <strong>conceptually and operationally</strong> (often with quantitative measures). For example, a conceptual goal might be “minimize CO emissions from cars,” while the operational version could be “minimize the average tons of CO emissions from cars over 12 months.”</p>

<p>I don’t think the book explains how this particular metric was determined. However, there are so many different ways to measure the same construct, and one should keep in mind the political economy of data—who decides what to measure and how. For example, the CO emisison example might be more scientific with fewer variations, but what if the construct is something latent, like student academic outcomes? Often, these are measured using standardized test scores and GPA, and that’s basically it. This choice actually imposes strong assumptions about what we mean by academic outcome. The plethora of ways to measure the outcome can completely change the story about whether a particular implementation is working or not, and what we are ultimately trying to achieve.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on selecting the criteria for evaluating the outcome and assessing the practicality of policy implementation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On constructing alternatives</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/policy-options.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On constructing alternatives" /><published>2025-09-30T00:15:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-30T00:15:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/policy-options</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/policy-options.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on constructing alternatives: brainstorming possible policy options.</p>

<p>Policy options should be comprehensive, though not necessarily mutually exclusive. The idea is to start with a broad list, then discard obvious nonstarters, combine or reorganize others into a basic alternative with possible variants. The book also offers helpful tips for making the list more comprehensive and creative:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>There are some helpful <strong>lists of actions governments</strong> can take for different types of problems (included in the appendix of the book). For example, in service provision, options might include adding a new service, expanding an existing one, reaching out to underserved groups, or tailoring services to specific subpopulations. These examples help stretch the imagination when brainstorming policy options.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Another approach is to use <strong>thought experiments by asking “what if”</strong> questions, such as “What if cost weren’t a constraint?”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Drawing analogies</strong> from other contexts can be helpful during the brainstorming phase. 
  However, I think in higher-stakes situations, it’s necessary to analyze whether the two cases are truly comparable. For example, claims like “Ukraine should surrender because it worked for Japan” are meaningless without a clear explanation of how the contexts align, which, in this case, they clearly don’t. Similarly, saying “Person A did this and it worked, so I must do it too” is risky logic. It’s fine to take inspiration from others, but always recognize that their circumstances are <em>never truly comparable</em> to your own. I often catch myself falling into this logic trap, so this is a note to self.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>What should always be concluded in the options is a <strong>“business-as-usual”</strong>. I suppose this serves as a baseline; any proposed alternative should ideally improve on the current problem (although it could introduce new problems), or at least not make things worse.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Policy analysts should also consider <strong>natural changes</strong> that could affect the scope of the problem, such as political shifts (e.g., after elections), business cycle fluctuations (e.g., unemployment), demographic trends (e.g., migration), or evolving technologies. This helps you consider policy options whilst accounting for inevitable changes, opening up possibilities that wouldn’t arise if you treated the current state as fixed.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Another option to include is <strong>“learn more”</strong>, which can involve running pilot programs, waiting for more information, or gathering stronger evidence.</p>

    <p>While this often sounds like an obvious good, almost like a mantra (especially in statistics conferences where strong evidence seems to be treated as indisputably rigorous and a good practice), I think it’s worth considering that there is a trade-off: what is the cost of inaction, or waiting for stronger evidence. Delays can have real, sometimes deadly consequences. For instance, delaying an organ transplant decision could mean losing both patients, where making a decision would have saved one life. Similarly, hesitation in providing military aid, such as the delayed defensive support to Ukraine pointed out during the Biden administration, resulted in loss of lives in Ukraine. Sometimes, the best decision is to make a decision, even with imperfect information. Of course, there’s also a flip side; some decisions made too quickly could have been much better with a bit of waiting. So it goes both ways. But again, since we’re in the brainstorming phase, the “learn more” option can stay for now; it might be ruled out later due to its known risks during later stages of the policy analysis.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If the options involve a <strong>continuum</strong>, like deciding appropriate rental rates for public housing, theoretically every penny change is a different option. A cleaner approach is to first establish the upper and lower limits of the acceptable range, then choose points within that range using ‘reasonable’ increments relative to the current rental rate (psychologically, an increment of around $25 might feel ‘right’).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Think about the mechanism of the problem.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Understanding the causal mechanism of a problem sounds like a necessary step to thinking about policy options or interventions, but <strong>understanding the causal mechanism actually not always required (!)</strong> Of course, it can be very helpful to understand the mechanism, as it helps narrow down possible intervention points, but it’s not always required or possible. For example, in the low vaccination example: if parents’ belief that vaccines cause autism is the actual reason their child is not vaccinated, the intervention to increase vaccination could still be something different, like imposing a school enrollment requirement.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Nonetheless, thinking about the mechanism of the problem, however complex, helps us better get a sense of its nature, potential interventions, and how those interventions might affect the situation. The book describes some basic models:</p>

        <p><strong>Market models</strong> — understanding flows like patients into hospitals in terms of <strong>supply and demand</strong>. Standard strategies to fix market problems usually involve raising or lowering prices faced by suppliers or demanders. In this example, it might mean increasing hospital bed availability, reducing demand by shifting care to home settings for less serious cases, and so on.</p>

        <p><strong>Production models</strong> — optimizing production to identify key factors affecting output, such as whether hiring more factory workers, having them work more hours (possible nightmare), or changing the assembly line order could increase efficiency.</p>

        <p><strong>Conformity models</strong> — peer effects where <strong>people adapt their actions based on those around them</strong>. For example, hanging posters in schools warning against suicide can fail because it may unintentionally normalize the behavior, making students think it’s common and acceptable. The book suggests effective interventions leverage this tendency to think and act like others.</p>

        <p>This last point made me think about controlling people’s beliefs and behaviors via online marketing, which I think raises new issues. Surely, it is effective for the one making the intervention and benefiting from the change, but I don’t think that should be the ultimate endpoint. Something to ponder.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>While compiling all these ideas into a comprehensive list helps ensure we don’t miss important action points, I’m wondering if it’s also possible to complement this with a quantitative approach (not to replace the qualitative work, but to support it, especially given how exhaustive this step is, and considering that we’re not in a high-stakes phase). For instance, we could input variables related to the problem and systematically apply different actions to each of them, all within the constraints and assumptions defined by the models above.</p>

<p>When creating policy options, it’s helpful to be <strong>detailed</strong>, especially about expected behaviors. Clearly describe what people involved in implementation would actually do differently compared to the current practice. For example, increasing facility inspections from once a year to twice a year.</p>

<p>Once all options are brainstormed and detailed, <strong>conceptualize and simplify</strong> them. The key to conceptualization is using simple sentences and plain, short phrases stripped of jargon. Then, distinguish between a basic strategy and its variants. I think this process helps <strong>reveal the underlying core structure and logic of policy options</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on constructing alternatives: brainstorming possible policy options.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On gathering evidence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/29/evidence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On gathering evidence" /><published>2025-09-29T19:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-29T19:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/29/evidence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/29/evidence.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on gathering evidence: information that helps answer the problem you have defined.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>All of your time doing a policy analysis is spent on two activities: thinking and hustling data that can be turned into evidence. Of these two activities, thinking is generally the more important, but hustling data takes much more time… the real-world settings in which policy analysis is done rarely afford the time for a research effort that would please a careful academic researcher. In fact, time pressure is probably almost as dangerous an enemy of high-quality policy analysis as is politically motivated bias, if not more so. Therefore, economize on your data collection activities. The key to economizing is this: try to collect only those data that can be turned into information that in turn can be converted into evidence. (p. 14)</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>What data do we actually need to answer the problem?</strong> – I think it’s oftentimes helpful to think in this way from the end goal backward, regardless of how much data or resources you have.</p>

<p>This kind of <strong>backward thinking</strong> is also relevant in sectors like IT, where creepy surveillance-level data on user behavior (that subjects themselves are unaware of providing) is available. In fact, the abundance of data can make analysis overly shaped or biased by what’s already available, as opposed to what is actually needed. When faced with large data, there’s a temptation that you <em>must</em> use what you already have—why look elsewhere when you have so much here? If the data does include what’s needed, that’s fine, but even if it doesn’t, thinking about the ideal data helps you identify the gap between what you have and what you actually need, which in turn <strong>reveals potential biases</strong> your analysis may be prone to.</p>

<p>When getting better acquainted with the problem, review existing literature not only for the key findings but also for the <strong>study’s strengths, limitations, and relevance to your specific context</strong>. Were there data they wanted to collect but couldn’t? Perhaps you can consider collecting that data if possible. Was the study conducted in a particular location? What are the similarities and differences between that location and yours?</p>

<p>Exploring related problems can also be helpful. For example, when studying how to reduce neighborhood resistance to low-income housing (such a Berkeley example!), it may be useful to review literature on community resistance to seemingly unrelated issues like solid waste incinerators, which may show <strong>instructive similarities</strong>.</p>

<p>When gathering information, be intentional about <strong>researching perspectives from those who might disagree</strong> with your problem definition or proposed solutions. Their perspectives can help uncover blind spots and fill in missing viewpoints. I hadn’t thought about doing this so early in the analysis; I assumed it came after a policy idea was formed, during implementation, to reduce resistance from the public. But in fact, it should start from the problem-definition and problem-review stage, by gathering information not only from those you agree with, but also from those you disagree with or don’t yet understand.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on gathering evidence: information that helps answer the problem you have defined.]]></summary></entry></feed>