<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-09-30T07:38:44-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">nyayava’s blog</title><subtitle>language, art, life, random thoughts
</subtitle><author><name>nyayava</name></author><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On projecting the outcome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On projecting the outcome" /><published>2025-09-30T07:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-30T07:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/project</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/project.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on projecting (or predicting) the outcome of each policy options.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>Projecting outcomes means making a <strong>reasonable prediction about the results</strong> of implementing a policy using sound methods. This can include building statistical models to estimate outcomes, applying common sense to suggest feasible ranges, or using qualitative reasoning such as case studies. The projection should include both the magnitude of the expected outcome and the uncertainty around it, often expressed as a range rather than a single point estimate.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>One useful approach is <strong>break-even (threshold) analysis</strong>, which <strong>sets a minimum bar for success</strong> by answering the question: “What is the least the policy must achieve to justify its cost? For example, if you have $1 million to reduce juvenile crime, you might ask whether a 1%, 5%, 10%, or 15% reduction would be enough to justify that investment. Then, you assess whether the policy can realistically achieve this minimum threshold, evaluate its plausibility, estimate the probability of failure, and consider the costs of accepting that failure.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Sensitivity analysis</strong> tests how outcomes change when input assumptions or variable values vary. It helps determine how much an assumption can change before the policy result falls outside the desired range.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When exact predictions aren’t feasible, <strong>scenario-based robust policy analysis</strong> can be used. This method compares a policy’s performance, without requiring precise predictions, across multiple future scenarios to identify options that perform reasonably well under a wide range of possible futures. This approach can be used for climate policy problems, where long-term analysis is required but the probability distribution of future climate outcomes is highly uncertain.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When projecting outcomes, beware of <strong>optimism bias</strong>; it’s the tendency to overlook risks and failures. Be realistic about potential future problems like budget cuts or unintended side effects.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I think there is also a phenomenon where implementing a policy can change people’s behavior that then affects the policy outcome.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’m interested in learning about qualitative methods for predicting outcomes, and in comparing them with quantitative approaches to understand when each is most useful.</p>

<p>There are a few more topics in this chapter, but I’ll leave it here for now.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on projecting (or predicting) the outcome of each policy options.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On selecting the criteria</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/criteria.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On selecting the criteria" /><published>2025-09-30T05:40:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-30T05:40:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/criteria</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/criteria.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on selecting the criteria for evaluating the outcome and assessing the practicality of policy implementation.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="criteria-for-evaluating-the-outcome">Criteria for evaluating the outcome</h4>
<p>This is the evaluative plotline, where you decide the criteria to assess the outcomes of a policy (not to be confused with criteria used to directly compare policy options, but rather to evaluate their projected outcomes first, which you then may compare).</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>A common criterion is <strong>efficiency</strong>, which in this case roughly translates to <strong>maximizing public interest</strong> (note that this differs from corporate efficiency which focuses on profit on one side).</p>

    <p>One way to measure efficiency is <strong>cost-effectiveness analysis (CE)</strong>, which assesses how well a policy achieves the desired quantity or nature of an output without assigning a monetary value to the outcome. My understanding is that CE analysis focuses on achieving a specific <strong>fixed outcome</strong> using the least resources or cost, or alternatively, uses <strong>fixed resources</strong> to compare different possible outputs. For example, in an earthquake-prone city upgrading building safety—a fixed desired outcome—the costs include disruption to residents. CE framework may propose to minimize these costs, like scheduling construction in one season rather than another, organizing so that not all stores are closed all at once, etc.</p>

    <p><strong>Cost-benefit analysis (CBA)</strong> evaluates the actual <em>value</em> of a policy’s outcomes in monetary terms. CBA calculates the net benefit by subtracting all costs from the total projected benefits, sometimes expressing this as a ratio. Because assigning monetary values to outcomes can be challenging, CEA is more commonly used.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Another evaluative criterion is <strong>equality, equity, fairness, or justice</strong>. These concepts aren’t defined in the book, but one example is affirmative action in university admissions. Some see it as promoting diverse learning environments or encouraging access to higher education for underrepresented groups. Others see it as unfair, especially if admission rates don’t reflect the proportion of applicants, disadvantaging larger groups with similar qualifications.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Other possible evaluative criteria include <strong>freedom</strong> (e.g., freedom from government interference, free markets, or capitalism).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Process values</strong> also matter, such as <strong>public participation, openness, transparency, and procedural fairness</strong>. However, note that greater participation doesn’t always mean more democracy, since those with more time and resources may disproportionately shape outcomes.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="prioritizing-evaluative-criteria">Prioritizing evaluative criteria</h4>
<p>There are three general approaches to weighting different evaluative criteria.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>One is to <strong>let existing government and officials decide</strong>, assuming they represent the interests of the public.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Another is for <strong>analysts to impose weights</strong> themselves, for example, to give more consideration to groups or values that may be underrepresented.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The third approach is to prioritize criteria based on <strong>rights</strong>, such as the right to privacy; however, which rights are valued can change over time and differ across societies.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="criteria-for-assessing-practicality">Criteria for assessing practicality</h4>
<p>While we’ve discussed criteria for assessing the outcomes of policy options, another type of criteria to consider is for assessing the practicality of implementing those options. The main ones are legality, political acceptability, administrative robustness, improvability, and policy sustainability.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Legality</strong> - policy must not violate constitutional or common law rights. This sounds obvious, but even this is violated these days under the current administration.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Political acceptability</strong> - in thinking about this, distinguish whether low acceptability comes from too much opposition or simply too little support; the latter could happen because of disinterest or lack of awareness, not necessarily opposition.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Robustness</strong> - whether the policy can still produce acceptable outcomes even with poor implementation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Improvability</strong> is about whether the policy leaves room to be improved over time, especially by those involved in implementation. This component makes policy analysis iterative rather than one-time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Policy sustainability</strong> seems related to robustness, but over time and across changing political leadership or environments.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>For all these criteria, it’s helpful to characterize them both <strong>conceptually and operationally</strong> (often with quantitative measures). For example, a conceptual goal might be “minimize CO emissions from cars,” while the operational version could be “minimize the average tons of CO emissions from cars over 12 months.”</p>

<p>I don’t think the book explains how this particular metric was determined. However, there are so many different ways to measure the same construct, and one should keep in mind the political economy of data—who decides what to measure and how. For example, the CO emisison example might be more scientific with fewer variations, but what if the construct is something latent, like student academic outcomes? Often, these are measured using standardized test scores and GPA, and that’s basically it. This choice actually imposes strong assumptions about what we mean by academic outcome. The plethora of ways to measure the outcome can completely change the story about whether a particular implementation is working or not, and what we are ultimately trying to achieve.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the reflection of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on selecting the criteria for evaluating the outcome and assessing the practicality of policy implementation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On constructing alternatives</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/policy-options.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On constructing alternatives" /><published>2025-09-30T00:15:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-30T00:15:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/policy-options</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/30/policy-options.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on constructing alternatives: brainstorming possible policy options.</p>

<p>Policy options should be comprehensive, though not necessarily mutually exclusive. The idea is to start with a broad list, then discard obvious nonstarters, combine or reorganize others into a basic alternative with possible variants. The book also offers helpful tips for making the list more comprehensive and creative:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>There are some helpful <strong>lists of actions governments</strong> can take for different types of problems (included in the appendix of the book). For example, in service provision, options might include adding a new service, expanding an existing one, reaching out to underserved groups, or tailoring services to specific subpopulations. These examples help stretch the imagination when brainstorming policy options.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Another approach is to use <strong>thought experiments by asking “what if”</strong> questions, such as “What if cost weren’t a constraint?”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Drawing analogies</strong> from other contexts can be helpful during the brainstorming phase. 
  However, I think in higher-stakes situations, it’s necessary to analyze whether the two cases are truly comparable. For example, claims like “Ukraine should surrender because it worked for Japan” are meaningless without a clear explanation of how the contexts align, which, in this case, they clearly don’t. Similarly, saying “Person A did this and it worked, so I must do it too” is risky logic. It’s fine to take inspiration from others, but always recognize that their circumstances are <em>never truly comparable</em> to your own. I often catch myself falling into this logic trap, so this is a note to self.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>What should always be concluded in the options is a <strong>“business-as-usual”</strong>. I suppose this serves as a baseline; any proposed alternative should ideally improve on the current problem (although it could introduce new problems), or at least not make things worse.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Policy analysts should also consider <strong>natural changes</strong> that could affect the scope of the problem, such as political shifts (e.g., after elections), business cycle fluctuations (e.g., unemployment), demographic trends (e.g., migration), or evolving technologies. This helps you consider policy options whilst accounting for inevitable changes, opening up possibilities that wouldn’t arise if you treated the current state as fixed.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Another option to include is <strong>“learn more”</strong>, which can involve running pilot programs, waiting for more information, or gathering stronger evidence.</p>

    <p>While this often sounds like an obvious good, almost like a mantra (especially in statistics conferences where strong evidence seems to be treated as indisputably rigorous and a good practice), I think it’s worth considering that there is a trade-off: what is the cost of inaction, or waiting for stronger evidence. Delays can have real, sometimes deadly consequences. For instance, delaying an organ transplant decision could mean losing both patients, where making a decision would have saved one life. Similarly, hesitation in providing military aid, such as the delayed defensive support to Ukraine pointed out during the Biden administration, resulted in loss of lives in Ukraine. Sometimes, the best decision is to make a decision, even with imperfect information. Of course, there’s also a flip side; some decisions made too quickly could have been much better with a bit of waiting. So it goes both ways. But again, since we’re in the brainstorming phase, the “learn more” option can stay for now; it might be ruled out later due to its known risks during later stages of the policy analysis.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If the options involve a <strong>continuum</strong>, like deciding appropriate rental rates for public housing, theoretically every penny change is a different option. A cleaner approach is to first establish the upper and lower limits of the acceptable range, then choose points within that range using ‘reasonable’ increments relative to the current rental rate (psychologically, an increment of around $25 might feel ‘right’).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Think about the mechanism of the problem.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Understanding the causal mechanism of a problem sounds like a necessary step to thinking about policy options or interventions, but <strong>understanding the causal mechanism actually not always required (!)</strong> Of course, it can be very helpful to understand the mechanism, as it helps narrow down possible intervention points, but it’s not always required or possible. For example, in the low vaccination example: if parents’ belief that vaccines cause autism is the actual reason their child is not vaccinated, the intervention to increase vaccination could still be something different, like imposing a school enrollment requirement.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Nonetheless, thinking about the mechanism of the problem, however complex, helps us better get a sense of its nature, potential interventions, and how those interventions might affect the situation. The book describes some basic models:</p>

        <p><strong>Market models</strong> — understanding flows like patients into hospitals in terms of <strong>supply and demand</strong>. Standard strategies to fix market problems usually involve raising or lowering prices faced by suppliers or demanders. In this example, it might mean increasing hospital bed availability, reducing demand by shifting care to home settings for less serious cases, and so on.</p>

        <p><strong>Production models</strong> — optimizing production to identify key factors affecting output, such as whether hiring more factory workers, having them work more hours (possible nightmare), or changing the assembly line order could increase efficiency.</p>

        <p><strong>Conformity models</strong> — peer effects where <strong>people adapt their actions based on those around them</strong>. For example, hanging posters in schools warning against suicide can fail because it may unintentionally normalize the behavior, making students think it’s common and acceptable. The book suggests effective interventions leverage this tendency to think and act like others.</p>

        <p>This last point made me think about controlling people’s beliefs and behaviors via online marketing, which I think raises new issues. Surely, it is effective for the one making the intervention and benefiting from the change, but I don’t think that should be the ultimate endpoint. Something to ponder.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>While compiling all these ideas into a comprehensive list helps ensure we don’t miss important action points, I’m wondering if it’s also possible to complement this with a quantitative approach (not to replace the qualitative work, but to support it, especially given how exhaustive this step is, and considering that we’re not in a high-stakes phase). For instance, we could input variables related to the problem and systematically apply different actions to each of them, all within the constraints and assumptions defined by the models above.</p>

<p>When creating policy options, it’s helpful to be <strong>detailed</strong>, especially about expected behaviors. Clearly describe what people involved in implementation would actually do differently compared to the current practice. For example, increasing facility inspections from once a year to twice a year.</p>

<p>Once all options are brainstormed and detailed, <strong>conceptualize and simplify</strong> them. The key to conceptualization is using simple sentences and plain, short phrases stripped of jargon. Then, distinguish between a basic strategy and its variants. I think this process helps <strong>reveal the underlying core structure and logic of policy options</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on constructing alternatives: brainstorming possible policy options.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On gathering evidence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/29/evidence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On gathering evidence" /><published>2025-09-29T19:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-29T19:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/29/evidence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/29/evidence.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuation of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on gathering evidence: information that helps answer the problem you have defined.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>All of your time doing a policy analysis is spent on two activities: thinking and hustling data that can be turned into evidence. Of these two activities, thinking is generally the more important, but hustling data takes much more time… the real-world settings in which policy analysis is done rarely afford the time for a research effort that would please a careful academic researcher. In fact, time pressure is probably almost as dangerous an enemy of high-quality policy analysis as is politically motivated bias, if not more so. Therefore, economize on your data collection activities. The key to economizing is this: try to collect only those data that can be turned into information that in turn can be converted into evidence. (p. 14)</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>What data do we actually need to answer the problem?</strong> – I think it’s oftentimes helpful to think in this way from the end goal backward, regardless of how much data or resources you have.</p>

<p>This kind of <strong>backward thinking</strong> is also relevant in sectors like IT, where creepy surveillance-level data on user behavior (that subjects themselves are unaware of providing) is available. In fact, the abundance of data can make analysis overly shaped or biased by what’s already available, as opposed to what is actually needed. When faced with large data, there’s a temptation that you <em>must</em> use what you already have—why look elsewhere when you have so much here? If the data does include what’s needed, that’s fine, but even if it doesn’t, thinking about the ideal data helps you identify the gap between what you have and what you actually need, which in turn <strong>reveals potential biases</strong> your analysis may be prone to.</p>

<p>When getting better acquainted with the problem, review existing literature not only for the key findings but also for the <strong>study’s strengths, limitations, and relevance to your specific context</strong>. Were there data they wanted to collect but couldn’t? Perhaps you can consider collecting that data if possible. Was the study conducted in a particular location? What are the similarities and differences between that location and yours?</p>

<p>Exploring related problems can also be helpful. For example, when studying how to reduce neighborhood resistance to low-income housing (such a Berkeley example!), it may be useful to review literature on community resistance to seemingly unrelated issues like solid waste incinerators, which may show <strong>instructive similarities</strong>.</p>

<p>When gathering information, be intentional about <strong>researching perspectives from those who might disagree</strong> with your problem definition or proposed solutions. Their perspectives can help uncover blind spots and fill in missing viewpoints. I hadn’t thought about doing this so early in the analysis; I assumed it came after a policy idea was formed, during implementation, to reduce resistance from the public. But in fact, it should start from the problem-definition and problem-review stage, by gathering information not only from those you agree with, but also from those you disagree with or don’t yet understand.</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a continuation of the 8-fold path for policy analysis described in A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). This section is on gathering evidence: information that helps answer the problem you have defined.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy Analysis - On definining the problem</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/28/policy-step-one.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy Analysis - On definining the problem" /><published>2025-09-28T15:15:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-28T15:15:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/28/policy-step-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2025/09/28/policy-step-one.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a reflection on <em>A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis</em> by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). The book gives a general framework for thinking through policy design and analysis. I’m interested in understanding how statistics, causal inference methods, and algorithmic tools can serve in the broader process of policymaking. The following includes paraphrased content from the book, along with my own questions and reflections.</p>

<p>The 8-fold path outlined in the book is:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Define the problem</li>
  <li>Assemble some evidence</li>
  <li>Construct the alternatives</li>
  <li>Select the criteria</li>
  <li>Project the outcomes</li>
  <li>Confront the trade-offs</li>
  <li>Stop, focus, narrow, deepen, decide</li>
  <li>Tell your story</li>
</ol>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="define-the-problem">Define the problem</h4>
<p>There’s no one-size-fits-all approach to problem definition. Instead, there are some pointers to help frame the problem and pitfalls to avoid.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Consider <strong>who is experiencing the problem?</strong> (the book calls this the issue of rhetoric). Problems are often framed by clients within a specific political context; they may define issues narrowly as technical issues or frame it in ways that deviates largely from the public. For example, the problem may be defined by those that are vocal or articulate, who may represent extreme positions. Policy analysts typically aim for a consensus using the normative standard of ‘maximizing overall welfare’.</p>

    <p>— I am curious about the benefit of defining a problem in a bottom-up way, as experienced by vulnerable groups who may not have the opportunity to voice their problems to appropriate platforms. That is, intentionally asking: whose voice is missing? And how can the societal system reduce their burden? This does not necessarily have to be a zero-sum situation, where the ‘other’ group is harmed. Everyone is vulnerable in some way. Centering the problem definition around the most vulnerable in a particular aspect under consideration could lead us to consider inclusive actions that benefit the majority, including the vulnerable. For example, having slopes in addition to (or instead of) stairs benefits not only those who use wheeled devices but also those who do not. 
  <!-- <span style="color:#888888;"></span> --></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Explain <strong>why does the problem matter?</strong> (the book describes it as ‘making the definition evaluative’). A problem means someone sees something wrong, but “wrong” is debatable. Even if everyone agrees on the facts, they may not agree those facts are a problem (!).</p>

    <p>For example, 65% of food consumed in Japan comes from abroad; some see this as a problem, others don’t. Also, some problems are so private or localized that government intervention may not help. The problem definition should explain why it matters, not just to a small group, but broadly to the public. Rephrasing the previous problem as ‘heavy reliance on imported food risks food supply’ This way, it becomes a shared concern of access to food. Potential causes of food supply disruption, like political or transport failures, are causal claims, so I’ll omit them from the problem definition for now.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Make the statement objective</strong> when possible. Problem definitions should include quantified features when possible; how much is too high or too little? For example, saying “too many people with annual incomes over $60k live in subsidized housing” is clearer than claims about the “relatively well-off.”</p>

    <p>My question is how is this number, $60k, determined? This itself requires research, as it likely depends on local housing costs, household expenses, etc.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Identify systemic problems</strong> when necessary (what book calls latent opportunities). Policy agendas are often driven by complaints, threats, or crises, and require reactive responses that treat the system as fixed. This may be like firefighters responding after a fire starts. In contrast, proactive approaches aim to prevent problems by addressing root causes and questioning the system’s underlying conditions. It’s not about one being more important than the other, but both are needed. When defining a problem, one can avoid narrowing the scope of opportunities to specific solution sets.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Don’t smuggle the solution</strong> into the problem definition. For example, saying “there is too little shelter for homeless families” assumes the solution is more shelters. Instead, state only the problem, like “too many families are homeless,” which allows for a wider range of possible solutions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Don’t smuggle the cause</strong> of the problem. For example, saying “too many parents believe vaccines cause autism” suggests that parents’ belief is the reason for low vaccination rates. However, changing beliefs may not be necessary, as a study indicates that simply requiring vaccines for school entry increased vaccination rates, regardless of beliefs.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>While defining the problem, we need to be aware of the <strong>limitations of the government intervention</strong>. Government intervention does not guarantee improvement, as its incentives may not lead to efficient outcomes or fair distribution. There are several sources of government failure:</p>
<ul>
  <li>In direct democracy, where citizens vote directly on policies, it can lead to the <strong>majority imposing high costs on minorities</strong>. While this may maximize overall welfare, it can harm smaller groups.</li>
  <li>In representative democracy, where citizens vote officials, the elected officials may be more <strong>influenced by organized groups</strong> than by the general public. Politicians often <strong>focus on short-term results</strong> to get reelected, rather than long-term policy effects.</li>
  <li>Rigid <strong>government procedures can impose restrictions</strong> on timeline, budget, and other resources, thereby limiting the range of realistic policy options to a small subset.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a reflection on A Practical Guide for Policy Analysis by Eugene Bardach and Eric M. Patashnik (6th edition, 2020). The book gives a general framework for thinking through policy design and analysis. I’m interested in understanding how statistics, causal inference methods, and algorithmic tools can serve in the broader process of policymaking. The following includes paraphrased content from the book, along with my own questions and reflections.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ウクライナの映画「Porcelain War」（陶の戦）</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ukraine/art/2025/09/28/porcelain.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ウクライナの映画「Porcelain War」（陶の戦）" /><published>2025-09-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ukraine/art/2025/09/28/porcelain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ukraine/art/2025/09/28/porcelain.html"><![CDATA[<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JPxIHYUXeEk?si=jcQwyvXCTbJpWZKe" width="650" height="370" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>「Porcelain War」（陶の戦）（2024年）は、戦争禍に生きる3人のウクライナ人芸術家の日常を追ったドキュメンタリー映画である。登場するのは、陶製の人形を作るスラバ、その人形に絵付けを施すアーニャ、そして油絵の風景を描くアンドリー。彼ら・彼女らは2022年のロシアによるウクライナ侵攻を機に、クリミアを離れ、ハルキウへと移る。アンドリーは妻と双子の娘をポーランドへ避難させ、自身はカメラマンとして戦時下の状況を記録し始める。スラバは武器を手に特殊部隊に参加し、アーニャはハルキウの住まいで創作活動を続けるのであった。</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="戦争当事者による内側からの視点を記録">戦争当事者による内側からの視点を記録</h4>
<p>撮影の特徴は、被写体自身が撮影を行うエスノグラフィー的な記録手法にある。それは、外部の観察者による報道的視点とは一線を画す、当事者自身の内側からの視点である。登場する芸術家たちは当初、撮影機材に不慣れだったが、撮影を始めるにあたり、時には任務の合間に地下壕に潜り、スターリンクのインターネット回線を通じて撮影方法の指導を受けながら技術を習得していった。彼ら・彼女らが操作するカメラやドローン、体に取り付けたGoProカメラによって実際に収められた映像素材は500時間を超える。特殊部隊の隊員が肩に装着したGoProで撮影された映像には、兵士が瓦礫の中を走り続け、地下の暗闇の中、負傷した仲間のもとへ駆けつける様子も収められている。その際に聞こえる独り言や息遣いから、内部の人々が直面する現実の一端が映し出されている。</p>

<p>ドキュメンタリーでは、特殊部隊の任務映像、任務先での日常、そして家に戻って行う穏やかな創作活動のシーンが交錯して映し出される。そこにはわかりやすい繋がりや起承転結はない。ただただ、極端に異なる状況を行き来する、混沌とした日々が記録されている。そんな中、アンドリーが妻と子どもをポーランドへ送り出す場面では、家族と離れて一人残された空虚感と、一方で家族が安全な場所にいるという安堵感が入り混じった、一言では表せない感情が語られる。ドキュメンタリーには、そうした整理しきれない入り組んだ心情も滲み出ている。</p>

<p>また、日常生活に戦争がいかに入り込んでいるのかも見えてくる。電気のない環境で、ろうそくのわずかな灯りのもと夜を過ごす様子や、爆撃音に反応して吠える飼い犬フロドの姿。食料を確保するために、スラバとアーニャがポルチーニ茸を探しに森へ向かう場面では、苔の下に地雷が埋まっており、かつて日常の一部だった森に自由に立ち入ることすら困難になっていることがわかる。地雷を発見したスラバは、地雷注意の標識を設置し、器用な手つきでゆっくりと解除していく。「生き延びるためには冷静さが必要だ」と彼は言う。</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_TGgRfsZIP0?si=jpE4GGyNKHqYpPTR" width="650" height="370" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="ウクライナがウクライナであり続けるための創作活動">ウクライナがウクライナであり続けるための創作活動　</h4>
<p>戦争が日常を蝕んでいく一方で、それでもなお、人々の生活を支えるものがある。自然や生き物、芸術、笑いが、戦争下に生きる人々にとって、癒しの薬となっている。スラバとアーニャが作った小さな子どもドラゴンの陶磁器の生き物を、兵士たちがお守りのように大切に手にする姿は印象的だ。ハルキウの自宅で、陶磁器の生き物を成形するスラバと、それに細やかな絵を描くアーニャたちの没頭した様子は、まるで瞑想をしているかのようだ。戦争についてアーニャは「この戦争によって、人の底知れぬ善良さが浮き彫りになった」とも言う。スラバは「人を怖がらせることはさほど難しくない。でも、生きることを封じるのは難しい。ウクライナはまるで陶磁器のようだ。傷つきやすいが、破壊することは決してできない」と続ける。</p>

<p>ドキュメンタリーに登場する芸術家たちの作品は、いずれも息を呑むほど美しい。アンドリーが描く<a href="https://www.andreystefanov.com/">クリミアの風景</a>は淡い色合いの世界が広がっていて、アーニャとスラバが作る<a href="https://www.porcelainbeasts.com/meet-the-beasts">陶磁器の生き物たち</a>は、まるまるとした愛らしい形をしていて、その艶やかな目にはまるで命が宿っているかのようだ。創作について、アーニャは「季節の変わり目に興味があり、自然からインスピレーションを受ける」と話している。彼女の細やかな筆遣いと、柔らかくも鮮やかな色彩の感性には魅了される。同時に、四季の移ろいを楽しむ日本の感覚とも通じる、どこか懐かしい親しみも感じられる。また、陶磁器に描かれた絵が動くシーンがあるが、これはポーランドのアニメーション会社によるものである。戦争に蝕まれる生き物の姿や、色鮮やかな世界を糸で紡ぐ描写は、実写の映像とはまた違った、慈しみ深い表現に感じる。</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2usJChoTjhI?si=vjqmoGQ2hQID59ZF" width="650" height="370" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>最後に、このドキュメンタリーの音楽は、四重奏団<a href="https://www.dakhabrakha.com.ua/en/about/">DakhaBrakha</a>によるウクライナ民族音楽である。DakhaBrakhaという名前は古代ウクライナ語で「与える／受け取る」を意味する。風や動物の声を模しているような抑揚と発声法には、個人的には保育園で学んだ<a href="https://youtu.be/piPXMt6j-yE?feature=shared">アイヌの民謡</a>を思わせる雰囲気を感じる。遠く離れたウクライナの芸術感性に、どこか日本の懐かしさが重なるようだった。民族音楽には、ウクライナという土地に根ざした自然と文化の長い時間の流れ、そしてそれを継承し育んできた人々の存在がある。その営みを、破壊しようと試みる侵略戦争。このドキュメンタリーは、ウクライナがウクライナであり続けるための、内側からの生活の記録である。</p>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cX8dyBKGGD4?si=Ai-JOQaim5c1UGOg" width="650" height="370" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/images/porcelain-film.jpg" alt="" style="max-width: 100%; height: auto;" />
  <figcaption>市内のウクライナ・ソーシャル・クラブで行われたドキュメンタリー上映会。ウクライナ系アメリカ人を中心に約40人が集まりました。</figcaption>
</div>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="ukraine" /><category term="art" /><category term="documentary" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">世界各地の独立系雑誌</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/culture/literature/2025/09/21/stack.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="世界各地の独立系雑誌" /><published>2025-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/culture/literature/2025/09/21/stack</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/culture/literature/2025/09/21/stack.html"><![CDATA[<p>ここ一年ほど、独立系雑誌をランダムに毎月届けてくれるサブスクリプション・サービス<a href="https://stackmagazines.com/shop/">「Stack Magazines（スタック・マガジンズ）」</a>を利用していました。文芸、ファッション、哲学、アートなどジャンルはさまざま。月の初めになると「今月はどんな雑誌が届くんだろう」と、ちょっとワクワクしてました。</p>

<p>雑誌には、担当者からの手紙が同封されていて、その号を選んだ理由が綴られています。それを読むと雑誌の背景がちょっとわかるので、読むときの入り口としてちょうどいい感じです。一冊の雑誌の中にはさまざまな人の作品が詰まっているので、ページをめくっていると、毎回何かしら目を引くものに出会います。</p>

<p>普段自分では手に取らないようなテーマの作品にも触れられるので、知らない場所に行って寄り道をしている感覚になります。はっとするような文章に出会うこともあれば、ときには意味がつかめず迷子になってしまうこともありますが、どれも普段凝り固まっている頭をぐにゃぐにゃとストレッチするような感覚を引き起こしてくれるような気がします。</p>

<p>以前、<a href="/ukraine/literature/2025/09/15/narnia">別の記事</a>で取り上げた、ウクライナ・ハルキウ市の詩人による詩「ナルニア」も、スタック・マガジンズを通して出会った作品のひとつでした。他にもいくつか印象に残っている雑誌を紹介します。</p>

<!-- add some line break, horizontal line, and another break -->
<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>
<hr style="width: 200px; margin: 10px auto; border: 0; border-top: 1px solid grey;" />

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>例えば、<a href="https://stackmagazines.com/magazine/al-hayya-2/">「Al Hayya」（الحيّة、アル・ハイヤ）</a>は、レバノン・ベイルート発の雑誌で、各ページにアラビア語と英語の両言語が並んでいます。この号のテーマはアラブ世界に生きる女性の身体で、ページをめくると、たとえば、ポールダンスを楽しむムスリムの看護師「Hijabiluscious」さんとの対談が掲載されています。「Al Hayya」は、アラビア語で「生きる」という意味だそうです。</p>

<div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 20px;">
</div>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/images/women1.jpg" alt="アル・ハイヤの雑誌の表紙には、アラブ世界に住む5人の女性がそれぞれ異なるファッションをまとって立っています。中央の女性は青いミニスカートのドレスにハイヒールを履き、腰に手を当てています。雑誌のタイトルは黄色で大きく、アラビア語と英語で表記されています。左側には18歳以上向けの内容であることが示されています。" style="max-width: 48%; height: auto;" />
  <img src="/images/women2.jpg" alt="雑誌をめくると、対談の一部があり、左ページにはヒジャブ姿でポールダンスをする女性の写真と彼女の英語の発言が掲載されています。右ページには同じ内容がアラビア語で書かれています。" style="max-width: 48%; height: auto;" />
  <figcaption style="text-align: justify;">雑誌の表紙は、5人の女性が各々のファッションをまとい立ち、黄色のタイトル文字が浮かび上がるデザイン。右の写真は、ポールダンスをするHijabilusciousさんとの対談記事の一部。自身のダンスをインスタグラムに投稿すると、誹謗中傷がつきまとうのだと言います。それに対する彼女の捉え方が印象的でした。「ポールダンサーであれば家父長制に加担していると言われ、肌を隠したら隠したでやっぱり家父長制の一端と言われる。では、いったいどちらなのか？私はそんな枠組みでの議論に乗る気がありません」とひと蹴り。読んでいてスカッとするような対談でした。雑誌には他にも、さまざまな方の対談記事や性に関する歴史的背景を探る読み物もあります。</figcaption>
</div>

<div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 50px;">
</div>

<!-- add some line break, horizontal line, and another break -->
<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>
<hr style="width: 200px; margin: 10px auto; border: 0; border-top: 1px solid grey;" />

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p><a href="https://stackmagazines.com/magazine/desired-landscapes-7/">「Desired Landscapes」</a>（思い描く風景）はギリシャ・アテネを拠点に置くポケットサイズのトラベルガイドのような雑誌。さまざまな場所を訪れた人たちの写真や絵、詩、エッセイが掲載されていたり、地図の表記方法など地形にまつわるテーマも取り上げています。</p>

<div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 10px;">
</div>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/images/landscapes1.jpg" alt="雑誌の表紙は、コンクリートを思わせる灰色で硬い質感。単色ながら光を反射する文字がアクセントになったシンプルなデザインです。" style="max-width: 48%; height: auto;" />
  <img src="/images/landscapes2.jpg" alt="さまざまな地図の表記法が紹介されているページ。上の地図は家を「C」、木を「D」と文字で表記していたり。下の地図では地形の輪郭に沿って、そこで人々がどのように定住していたのかの説明文そのものが地図に載っています。どの情報を切り取ってどう表すか、いろいろなビジュアル化があります。" style="max-width: 48%; height: auto;" />
  <figcaption style="text-align: justify;">雑誌の表紙は、コンクリートを思わせる灰色で硬い質感。単色ながら光を反射する文字がアクセントになったシンプルなデザインです。右の写真は、さまざまな地図の表記法が紹介されているページ。上の地図は家を「C」、木を「D」と文字で表記していたり。下の地図では地形の輪郭に沿って、そこで人々がどのように定住していたのかの説明文そのものが地図に載っています。どの情報を切り取ってどう表すか、いろいろなビジュアル化があります。　</figcaption>
</div>
<div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 20px;">
</div>

<!-- add some line break, horizontal line, and another break -->
<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>
<hr style="width: 200px; margin: 10px auto; border: 0; border-top: 1px solid grey;" />

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p><a href="https://kajetjournal.com/thefutureof/product/the-future-of-ghosts/">「The Future of Ghosts」</a>（幽霊の未来）は、ルーマニア・ブカレストで出版されている、さまざまなものの未来を想像するという、哲学的な問いを扱う雑誌です。この号は幽霊に焦点を当てていて、なぜ人は幽霊を想像するのか、どのように幽霊現象を記録してきたのか、またどのような現象が幽霊として説明されるのかが綴られています。</p>

<p>中には、2022年2月24日のロシア軍によるキーウ攻勢に関連して、ロシア軍機6機を撃墜したとされるウクライナの一人のパイロット、通称「キーウの幽霊」についても触れられています。ただ、これはもともとゲーム画面の動画から生まれた都市伝説なので、実際に一人のパイロットによって行われたものではないことが判明しています。にもかかわらず、当時このエピソードはSNSを通じて一気に拡散され、ウクライナの想像を超える抵抗を象徴する存在として語られるようになりました。ここでいう幽霊はパイロットを指したものだけでなく、デジタル空間にぶわっと現れる、本物なのか幻なのか判然としうない情報や、人々が信じたいと思う情報までもが「幽霊」として捉えることができるのではないかと思い、とても興味深かったです。</p>

<div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 20px;">
</div>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/images/ghosts1.jpg" alt="表紙には灰色の人間の顔が大きくアップで映し出されており、タイトル文字の背景には、亡霊のようにぼんやりと滲む白い光のエフェクトがかかっています。" style="max-width: 48%; height: auto;" />
  <img src="/images/ghosts2.jpg" alt="読者に向けられた一ページ目。フランケンシュタインの写真とメッセージが掲載されている。" style="max-width: 48%; height: auto;" />
  <figcaption style="text-align: justify;">一ページ目にはフランケンシュタインの写真と読者へのメッセージがあります。</figcaption>
</div>

<div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 50px;">
</div>

<p>なぜ幽霊について取り上げるのか。その手がかりとして、雑誌の読者へのメッセージの一部を紹介して終わりにしたいと思います。</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>「読者へ。幽霊への渇望は、現代社会への不満の表れであり、今という時間がつかみどころのないものとなり、未来が不毛に感じられていることの兆候でもある。ここでいう幽霊への関心は、時代遅れやただの奇妙なもの好きといった、周縁的な奇癖ではなく、まさに時代が抱える本質的な状態を映し出すものだ。</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>幽霊という存在は、私たちの絶え間ない変化への欲求や、ある何かに抱く懐かしさによって育まれている。その「何か」は、まだ実在していないかもしれないが、想像し、やがて形にすることもできる。幽霊の幻影は、現実か不可能かすら定かでない風景の中を進む私たちの案内人であり、未知なもの・予測不能なもの・目に見えないものを思索することが、決して異端ではないということを思い出させてくれる存在なのだ。」</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Dear reader, Longing for ghosts is a symptom of discontent with modern society, an indication that the present has become ungraspable and the future sterile. Our interest in ghosts is not a fringe eccentricity that signifies backwardness or sheer fascination with the obscure, but a consequential condition of our times.</p>

<p>This spectral figure of the ghost is, in fact, fed by our constant craving for change, by a nostalgia for a certain something. This certain something may not exist yet, but it can be imagined and then shaped. The ghost is our guide through (im)possible terrains in the making, our reminder that contemplating the unknown, the unpredictable, and the unseen is not some sort of heresy.”</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="culture" /><category term="literature" /><category term="book" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ここ一年ほど、独立系雑誌をランダムに毎月届けてくれるサブスクリプション・サービス「Stack Magazines（スタック・マガジンズ）」を利用していました。文芸、ファッション、哲学、アートなどジャンルはさまざま。月の初めになると「今月はどんな雑誌が届くんだろう」と、ちょっとワクワクしてました。]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ウクライナのビール</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ukraine/culture/2025/09/20/beer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ウクライナのビール" /><published>2025-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ukraine/culture/2025/09/20/beer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ukraine/culture/2025/09/20/beer.html"><![CDATA[<p>先日、ウクライナ系アメリカ人が経営するバーで、ウクライナのビールをいただきました。バーは地下にある隠れ家のような雰囲気で、カウンターにはウクライナの伝統的な陶器や食器類が展示されていました。</p>

<p>ウクライナのビールは5種類ほどあり、どれにしようか迷っていると、ウクライナの家庭で育ったという店員さんが、気前よくそれぞれのビールの特徴を丁寧に教えてくれました。</p>

<p>その中から、「フローラルで軽くて、最近のお気に入り」と定員さんがいう Mykhola Draft 1878（Микола、ミコラ） を選んでみました。ボトルのラベルは紫色。グラスに注がれると、爽やかな黄金色とのコントラストがとてもきれいです。たしかに味はフルーティーで苦味はほとんどなく、すっきりとしています。バーに立ち寄る前にウクライナの民謡ダンスを体験してきたのですが、想像以上にハードでたっぷり汗をかいて、喉も渇いていたので、とても爽快に感じました。</p>

<p>別の日に訪れた際には、Obolon Svitle（オボロン・ライト、Оболонь Світле）を飲んでみました。麦芽の香ばしい風味が鼻に抜ける感じで、後からほんのりとした苦味を感じました。話をしながらゆっくり飲んでいたら、最後にはぬるくなってしまい、普段全くビールを飲まない自分としては、冷たいうちにさっと飲み切るのがいいのだと学びました。</p>

<p style="display: flex; gap: 10px;">

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/images/beer-mykhola.jpg" alt="紫色のラベルが印象的なミコラビールのボトルの横に、黄金色のビールが注がれたグラスが並ぶ。" style="max-width: 38%; height: auto;" />
  <img src="/images/beer-obolon.jpg" alt="オボロン・ライトの緑色の缶。背後のバーカウンターには、リキュールなどさまざまな種類のお酒がずらりと並んでいる。" style="max-width: 38%; height: auto;" />
  <figcaption>紫のラベルのボトルはミコラ・ドラフト、緑の缶はオボロン・ライトです</figcaption>
</div>



<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

バーには他にも Lvivske 1715 （Львівське、リヴィウスケ）や ウォッカのカクテルもあるようなので、機会あれば今後も試してみたいと思います。
</p>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="ukraine" /><category term="culture" /><category term="food" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[先日、ウクライナ系アメリカ人が経営するバーで、ウクライナのビールをいただきました。バーは地下にある隠れ家のような雰囲気で、カウンターにはウクライナの伝統的な陶器や食器類が展示されていました。]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ウクライナの曲「ВДОМА」(ふるさとで)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ukraine/culture/2025/09/17/vdoma.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ウクライナの曲「ВДОМА」(ふるさとで)" /><published>2025-09-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ukraine/culture/2025/09/17/vdoma</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ukraine/culture/2025/09/17/vdoma.html"><![CDATA[<p>最近よく聴いているのが、ウクライナのバンド「АНТИТІЛА（アンティティラ）」の曲。5人組のグループで、メンバーは実際にウクライナ軍の医療隊員として従軍していた経験を持つ。今は音楽を通して、ウクライナの人々の士気を高め、得た収益は軍の支援に充てている。ちなみに、「アンティティラ」は「抗体 (antibodies)」という意味。侵攻に抗い、国の文化や人々の生活の潤いを防衛する姿は、まさにウクライナ体内の抗体のようだ。</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5cMFArN3HdE?si=u93cKf4pJxVeG61h" width="650" height="370" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>「ВДОМА」の曲名の意味は「At Home」「ふるさとで」。ふるさとを離れて暮らしている人々が、記憶や夢の中でふるさとを思い出している、という内容だと解釈しています。</p>

<p>動画に映し出される場所には、白い鳥に囲まれたマリウポリの<a href="https://awards.mediaarchitecture.org/mab/project/284">自由広場</a>、彫刻が豪華な<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odesa_Passage">オデッサのパッセージ</a>（商店が並ぶ通り）、クリミア半島の絶壁の城・<a href="https://tabinodaiziten.com/superb-view-of-europe/category143/entry548.html">スワローズ・ネスト</a>、ヘルソン市の入り口の看板、ヴィーンヌィツャにある赤レンガの<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vinnytsia_water_tower">給水塔</a>、<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Square_of_Contracts_(Kyiv)">コントラクトヴァ広場</a>の観覧車…ビデオを見ていると、街の美しい建造物や豊かな自然に魅了されることもさることながら、住宅街に干された色鮮やかな洗濯物など、ふと漂う素朴な生活感にどこか親しみやすさも感じます。</p>

<p>コメントの中には「泣いてしまうのがわかっていたから、動画を観るのをずっとを躊躇していました。でもやっと今になってみましたが、スワローズ・ネストをみた途端、泣き崩れてしまいました。毎晩のように、故郷であるクリミア南部の海沿いの村が夢に出てきます。そこは、世界で最も美しい場所です。もしもう一度あの場所をこの目で見ることができたら、最高の幸せを感じると思う 」</p>

<p>”Я відтягувала перегляд просто тому, що знала. Буду ридати. Наважилася подивитися тільки зараз. Але я трималася до моменту, як побачила Ластівниче гніздо. Після цього кадру мене розірвало на шмаття. Я майже кожної ночі бачу уві снах рідне селище на південному узбережжі Криму. Це найкрасивіше місце в світі, повірте мені. Якщо колись я матиму можливість побачити його знову, я буду найщасливішою людиною на планеті”（＠ksenya_danch）</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>意訳ですが、歌詞の中にはこのような表現があります　</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>いったいどれほどいるのだろう<br />
違う場所と時に流れ着いた私たち<br />
それでも、地球上でもっとも美しい場所へと<br />
引き寄せられ、夢にみる</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>ふるさとの空はどこまでも青く<br />
ふるさとの空には自由が宿ってる<br />
ふるさとにいると考えが晴れ渡る<br />
みんな、どこまでも私たちの一員　</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>О скільки ж нас?<br />
Нас приїжджих в інше місце й час<br />
Та тягне так і сняться сни<br />
Про найкраще місце на землі</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Вдома небо синє синє<br />
Вдома в небі воля дихає<br />
Вдома думи ясні ясні<br />
Свої, свої, свої, і всі свої</p>
</blockquote>

<p>「Свої」の意味ですが、英語では「our own」と訳されるようです。（ウクライナ語初心者なので、英語の方のニュアンスをもとに考えると）何かが自分のものだという意味というよりは、誰かが自分たちの仲間であるという意味合いが強いです。歌詞全体の内容から考えると、離れ離れになっているけど、同じ価値観・思い出・属性を共有するウクライナの人々を包み込むような表現だと解釈しています。</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>また、こちらはウクライナ国内で行われたライブバージョン。</p>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe width="650" height="350" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RG8R_tOktyY?si=V9H5-k51a1aUmxEs" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p>リズムに乗って立ち上がる子どもたち、国旗を掲げる人、ライトを何度も高く掲げる人、パートナーを抱き寄せる負傷した兵士 - みんながひとつになって音楽を楽しんでいる様子が見られます。戦時下だからこそ、日々の生活を送り、楽しむことを忘れない - とても難しいことですが、それを続けることこそが戦争に対する、ある意味で、最も強力な抵抗なのかもしれません。この映像を見ていると、音楽は祈りなのだと感じさせられます。</p>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<p><a href="https://antytila.com/en/all-videos-en/">アンティティラの公式ウェブサイト</a>および<a href="https://antytila.com/en/about/">メンバー紹介</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>ボーカル：タラス・トポリャ  (Taras Topolia / Тарас Тополя)</li>
  <li>キーボード： セルヒー・ウスィク  (Serhii Vusyk / Сергій Вусик)</li>
  <li>ギター: ドミトロ・ジョールドゥ (Dmytro Zholud / Дмитро Жолудь)</li>
  <li>バス: ミハイロ・チルコ  (Mykhailo Chyrko / Михайло Чирко)</li>
  <li>ドラム: ドミトロ・ヴォドヴォゾフ  (Dmytro Vodovozov / Дмитро Водовозов)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="ukraine" /><category term="culture" /><category term="music" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[最近よく聴いているのが、ウクライナのバンド「АНТИТІЛА（アンティティラ）」の曲。5人組のグループで、メンバーは実際にウクライナ軍の医療隊員として従軍していた経験を持つ。今は音楽を通して、ウクライナの人々の士気を高め、得た収益は軍の支援に充てている。ちなみに、「アンティティラ」は「抗体 (antibodies)」という意味。侵攻に抗い、国の文化や人々の生活の潤いを防衛する姿は、まさにウクライナ体内の抗体のようだ。]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ウクライナの詩「Нарнія」(ナルニア)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ukraine/literature/2025/09/15/narnia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ウクライナの詩「Нарнія」(ナルニア)" /><published>2025-09-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-09-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ukraine/literature/2025/09/15/narnia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ukraine/literature/2025/09/15/narnia.html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="ナルニア">ナルニア</h4>
<p>ウクライナの詩人、ドミトリー・ブリズニュークによる詩『ナルニア』より一節：</p>

<div style="margin-top: 20px;"></div>

<blockquote style="font-size: 17px; line-height: 2;">
今日ははだかで眠ることにしよう  <br />
ただの夫婦　恋人のように   <br />
服を全てぬいで   <br />
ズボンにカーディガン　スウェット <br />
パーカーには   <br />
パスポート　薬　USBメモリ　現金   <br />
カギ　クレジットカード　ケータイの充電器が   <br />
入ってる   <br />
くつもくつしたも　ぬいで  <br /> 
夜中にロケットが家を直撃することを恐れずに   <br />
生きのびて   <br />
ポーランドへ　ナルニアへ  <br />
星あかりの冬の闇をくぐりぬけて　ひなんしなければ   <br />
それよりも　今夜は平和なくらしの   <br />
祭りの宣言をしよう  <br />
はだかになって抱き合い　なにもかも気にせずに眠ろう   <br />
私たちの肌が   <br />
体が信頼とやさしさを思い出せるように   <br />
今日は一晩だけでも戦争のスイッチを切ろう   <br />
</blockquote>

<!-- add some line break, horizontal line, and another break -->
<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>
<hr style="width: 200px; margin: 10px auto; border: 0; border-top: 1px solid grey;" />

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="narnia">Narnia</h4>
<p>Exercpt from <em>Narnia</em>, by Dmitry Blizniuk, a Ukrainian poet based in Kharkiv<br />
Translated from Russian by Yana Kane<br />
Edited by Bruce Esrig</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>today let us go to sleep naked<br />
like an ordinary husband and wife like lovers<br />
take off all our clothes pants cardigans sweats parkas<br />
stuffed<br />
with passports medicines flash drives cash<br />
keys credit cards cell phone chargers<br />
let us take off our shoes and socks let us<br />
not fear that during the night a rocket will hit our home<br />
but we will survive and have to run<br />
through the starlit winter darkness into poland into narnia<br />
instead let us declare this evening a festival<br />
of peaceful life<br />
strip naked embrace and fall asleep without a care<br />
let our skin<br />
our bodies remember trust tenderness<br />
this day let us switch off the war for at least one night</p>
</blockquote>

<!-- add some line break, horizontal line, and another break -->
<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>
<hr style="width: 200px; margin: 10px auto; border: 0; border-top: 1px solid grey;" />

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="нарнія"><em>Нарнія</em></h4>
<p>уривок<br />
Дмитро Близнюк</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>давай сьогодні ляжемо спати голі<br />
як нормальні чоловік і дружина як коханці<br />
знімемо усі речі штани кофти куртки набиті<br />
паспортами ліками флешками готівкою <br />
ключами кредитками зарядками для мобільників <br />
знімемо взуття шкарпетки давай сьогодні <br />
не будемо боятися що вночі до нашої оселі <br />
прилетить снаряд а ми виживемо і нам доведеться бігти <br />
крізь зимову зіркову в Польщу Нарнію давай <br />
сьогодні ввечері влаштуємо свято  <br />
мирного життя<br />
роздягнемося догола обіймемося і спокійно заснемо <br />
нехай наша шкіра <br />
і тіла згадають довіру ніжність <br />
давай сьогодні хоч на одну ніч вимкнемо війну</p>
</blockquote>

<!-- add some line break, horizontal line, and another break -->
<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>
<hr style="width: 200px; margin: 10px auto; border: 0; border-top: 1px solid grey;" />

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="詩の背景">詩の背景　</h4>

<p>『ナルニア』が書かれたのは、ロシアによるウクライナ侵略が始まったばかりの2022年3月です。ウクライナ東部の都市ハルキウが、激しい攻撃にさらされる中、現地に暮らす詩人ドミトリー・ブリズニュークさんによって書かれました。原文を読むと、カンマがなかったり、行の切れ目が不揃いなのがわかります。ドミトリーさん曰く「砲撃の最中と、爆撃の合間の静けさの中で、思いつくままに書きました。今、殺されるかもしれない、あるいは1時間後かもしれない。そんな状況が延々と続いているという、暗く狂った現実をそのまま伝えるために、あえて修正はしませんでした」</p>

<p>ハルキウはロシア国境に近いこともあって、住民の多くがロシア語を話す地域でした。この詩も最初はロシア語で書かれていました。その元のロシア語の英訳を手がけたのが、旧ソ連出身で今はアメリカに暮らすヤナ・ケインさん。私は彼女の英訳を2023年10月に刊行されたアメリカの文芸誌 <a href="https://stackmagazines.com/magazine/american-chordata-13/"><em>American Chordata</em></a> で読みました。ヤナさんは他にも、戦争下で生きている人々のロシア語の文章の英訳を手がけており、詳しくは、<a href="https://worldliteraturetoday.org/blog/translation/different-coin-equal-sum-translating-kopilka-poetry-witness-and-antiwar-protest">World Literature Today の記事</a>で読むことができます。</p>

<p>ウクライナにはロシア語を母語とする人が多いものの、最近は意識的にウクライナ語を使う人が増えているようです。この詩もロシア語からウクライナ語に書き直されており、その原文と英訳は、雑誌 <em>the other side of hope</em> の<a href="https://othersideofhope.com/uploads/1/3/7/3/137328322/dmitry_blizniuk.pdf">ウェブサイト</a>で読むことができます。</p>

<!-- add some line break, horizontal line, and another break -->
<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>
<hr style="width: 200px; margin: 10px auto; border: 0; border-top: 1px solid grey;" />

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="想像される状況">想像される状況　</h4>

<p>戦争は4年目に入ったけれど、詩に書かれているような状況は今も続いている。夜中は毎日のように空襲警報が鳴り、ミサイルによって民間人がランダムに死んでいく、生殺しのような状況。そんな中でも、日常を自分らしく生きようとする人々がいる。ウクライナの外の世界では、「戦争はまだまだ続くだろう」と最もらしい予測が語られるが、実際にこの生活を強いられている渦中の人々にとって、その言葉を聞くのは堪え難い状況なのではないかと想像する。ヨーロッパの人々が静かな夜を過ごしていられるのは、静かな夜を必死に求めながらも、ウクライナの土地で暮らし続けているウクライナの人々がいるからなのだ。</p>

<p>しかし、ウクライナの限界が訪れたとき、それがヨーロッパにとって何を意味するのか–さらには、軍事力の強い国を近くに抱える日本を含む他の国々にとって、どんな意味を持つのかを考えると、これはもう自分ごととして捉えざるを得ない。力の強いものが、弱いものの痛みや犠牲の上に富と力を搾取し、それは仕方のないことだからと座視されてしまう世界。</p>

<p>そんな世界に私は住みたくないし、そうした世界に向かわせようとする人を助けたいとも思わない。個人でできることは限られているように感じるが、日々の生活や発言においては、自立を心がけることはできる。生活面において誰かに依存することを減らし、権威を持つ人の発言を鵜呑みにせず、最終的には自分で考えて判断することを意識する。また、自分自身や周りの人に優しい気持ちを持ち、必要があれば人に頼り、頼られたときにはできるだけ応えるようにする。ウクライナについては、たとえば、防空や国内ジャーナリズムへの送金、買い物を通じた経済・文化の関与、ニュースや書籍を通して知り続け、考え続ける。仕事においては、私の場合、研究ですが、困難な状況に置かれている人たちが抱える問題を調査・可視化し、解決策を探るような要素を取り組む。</p>

<p>そう考えると個人でもやれることはかなりある。ただ、やったことに対する結果がどうなるかはわからないし、むしろ結果なんて見えないまま進むことの方が多いだろう。それは、ナルニアのように現実には存在しない夢物語かもしれない。それでも、混沌の中にあっても、そんな社会を想像しながら歩みつづけるという絶え間ない運動が生きるということなのではないか。</p>

<!-- add some line break, horizontal line, and another break -->
<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>
<hr style="width: 200px; margin: 10px auto; border: 0; border-top: 1px solid grey;" />

<div style="margin-top: 40px;"></div>

<h4 id="訳について">訳について</h4>

<p>詩の和訳は、英訳をもとにしました。ただ、伝言ゲームのように意味がずれていくことのないように、ウクライナ語の原文も初心者なりに一語一句確認しながら、英訳との大きなズレがないか見ました。</p>

<p>ただ、この詩は「砲撃の最中と、爆撃の合間の静けさの中で、思いつくままに」書かれたものなので、原文にはが表記の乱れがあります。その状況を想像しながら訳を考えました。</p>

<ul>
  <li>表記の乱れ　
    <ul>
      <li>原文にはほんど句読点がなく、小文字のみで書かれていて、行の切れ目にも揺らぎがあります。急いで書かれたのかもしれません。噛み締めるように書いたところもあるのかもしれません。ただ、それをそのまま句読点がない日本語にすると読みづらいので、代わりにスペースを入れました。</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>漢字、ひらがな、カタカナの選択
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>ドミトリーさんによると、当時は停電が続いていたそうで、元が手書きかどうかははっきりしませんが、手書きだったのではないかと想像して訳しています。日本語を手書きで思いつくままに書く場合、画数の多い漢字は少し時間がかかるため避けるだろうと考えました。また、漢字にするとどうしても正式な印象が強くなり、それがこの詩の持つ切迫感とずれてしまうため、基本的に画数の多い漢字はひらがなかカタカナにしています。</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>ただ、漢字はピクトグラムのように、視覚的に意味を訴えてくる力があります。「直撃」「闇」「戦争」といった漢字を見ると、瞬時に重みと破壊力が伝わってくる気がします。書くときにも少し時間がかかる漢字だからこそ、詩の中に感じた延々と続く辛さとつながっているように思い、これらの言葉はあえて漢字表記にしました。</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>一方で、ひらがなにすると、言葉にふっと儚さが宿るように感じます。詩からは、平穏な時間の儚さを感じたので、「くらし」はひらがなで表記しています。</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>日本語には各言葉に、漢字・ひらがな・カタカナの選択肢があるため、その点においては、ウクライナ語やロシア語、英語よりも表現の幅が広がると感じました。逆に言えば、原文にない表現を訳者が作り出す部分がどうしてもあります。今回は、私が英訳を読んで感じたことを日本語で表現しています。</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>言い回しの選択　
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>「寝よう」と「眠ろう」のどちらを使うかについてですが、「寝よう」は日常的に使う表現で軽い感じがする一方、「眠ろう」はより意図的な行為に感じたので後者を選びました。また、「眠ろう」という言葉は、ただ安らかに眠るという意味だけでなく、もしかしたら死んでしまうかもしれない、永遠の眠りについてしまうかもしれないという、不安定でぎりぎりの状況を連想させる気がします。</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>ウクライナ語の「як нормальні чоловік і дружина」にある「нормальні（ノルマーリニ）」のニュアンスがわからないのですが、英訳では「like an ordinary husband and wife」となっています。ただ、日本語で「平凡な夫婦」と訳すと、文化的な違いからか、「平凡な夫婦」と「裸で寝る」が同じ感覚で語られることに少し引っかかりがありました。ここでの「normal, ordinary」はあくまでも平凡な状況下でのありのままの姿を指しているのだと思い、ぴったりではないですが「ただの夫婦」としました。</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>nyayava</name></author><category term="ukraine" /><category term="literature" /><category term="poem" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ナルニア ウクライナの詩人、ドミトリー・ブリズニュークによる詩『ナルニア』より一節：]]></summary></entry></feed>